A Guide to the Wine Family Papers, 1899-1943
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Wine Family Papers, 1899-1943
Library of Virginia
42353
2.7 cu. ft. (5 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
John E. Wine was born 31 July 1899, near Forestville, Shenandoah County, Virginia, to Rev. Daniel P. Wine and Rebecca Good Wine. He attended Bridgewater College, 1911, and the Medical College of Virginia, 1917. After college he did his post-graduate work at the Rockefeller Institute and Columbia University, New York. During World War I he enlisted with the Medical Reserve Corps and served in France, 1918-1919. After the war he opened a practice in Harrisonburg, Virginia. On 11 May 1918 he married Nell S. Fennell. He died in Harrisonburg on 1 March 1967.
Nell S. Fennell was born 11 July 1898, to David Carey Fennell and Minnie Newkirk Fennell of Kerr, North Carolina. She attended the North Carolina Normal School (later University of North Carolina Greensboro). They had one son, Jean Fennell Wine, born 24 July 1920. She died 13 January 1953.
Mary McKay Shuford (b. 1920) grew up in Harrisonburg, Virginia, raised by her aunt and uncle, John E. Wine and Nell Wine. Mrs. Wine and Mary Shuford's mother were sisters. Mary Shuford's father was Dr. Edward L. Shuford a veterinarian in Asheville, North Carolina. In 1925 Mary's mother, Jean Fennell Shuford, died, and Mary went to live with the Wine family. In 1943 she married Dr. John J. Dobbie of Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1899-1943, of the Wine Family of Harrisonburg, Virginia, including John Eugue Wine, his wife, Nell Fennell Wine, and their niece, Mary McKay Shuford Dobbie. The papers are arranged into three series: John E. Wine Papers, 1899-1933; Nell Fennell Wine Papers, 1910-1919; and Mary McKay Shuford Dobbie Papers, 1920-1943. Included are agreements, certificates, correspondence, military records, notebooks, photographs, receipts, school records, scrapbooks, and wedding cards.
The John E. Wine Papers, 1899-1933, document his military service in France and education and medical career in Rockingham County, Virginia. Included are certificates, notebooks, and report cards regarding his education at Bridgewater College and the Medical College of Virginia. Three volumes of notebooks containing medical notations from his service during World War I. Also included are estate papers and will of his father's, Daniel P. Wine (d. 1923) and notices, reports, and financial statements, 1930-1932, of Havey System, Inc. of Clifton Forge, Virginia.
His military records, 1918-1929, include appointments, leave passes, orders, personal reports, photographs, and telegrams. The correspondence, 1911-1933, mostly consists of letters written to his wife, Nell Wine, during post graduate work in New York and military service in the United States and France.
The Nell Fennell Wine Papers, 1910-1919, includes correspondence from friends and report cards and school work from the North Carolina Normal College (Greensboro, NC).
The Mary McKay Shuford Dobbie Papers, 1920-1943, include certificates, correspondence, photographs, school work, and scrapbooks. Included are notes and report cards from Harrisonburg High School and Madison College in Harrisonburg, Virginia. The correspondence includes letters from her father, Edward L. Shuford, and future husband, John Dobbie. Also included are photographs of friends and graduation at Madison College and wedding cards from their wedding in 1943. The scrapbooks include correspondence, invitations, photograhs, and various ephemera.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series: Series I. John E. Wine Papers, 1899-1933; Series II. Nell Fennell Wine Papers, 1910-1919; and Series III: Mary McKay Shuford Dobbie Papers, 1920-1943.
Contents List
- Series I: John Eugene Wine Papers, 1899-1933
  - Agreements, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business cards, nd (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1908-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1911-1919 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1919 June-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Estate of D.P. Wine, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harvey System, Inc., 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medical studies and research, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memberships, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Military records, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Military records, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Military records, 1924-1929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Receipts, 1926-1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Report cards, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notebooks, History notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks, Medical school (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, Medical school (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks, Medical school (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks, WWI (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II: Nell Fennell Wine Papers, 1914-1919
  - Calling card and envelope, nd (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - School work, 1910-1916 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series III: Mary McKay Shuford Dobbie Papers, 1920-1943
  - Certificates, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Cards, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, nd (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, c. 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, c. 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, c. 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, c. 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Report cards, 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - School work, nd (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Wedding cards, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Wedding cards, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Wedding cards, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbooks, 1935-1943 (Box 5)